

Doris M.
Backend Engineer

General info

Work experience Location

6 years total Nairobi, Kenya

Time zone: UTC+3

Top technologies

Java	5+ years experience	12345+
Spring Boot	5+ years experience	12345+
PostgreSQL	5+ years experience	12345+
JPA	5+ years experience	12345+
MongoDB	4 years experience	1 2 3 4 5+

Technologies



Bio

Main areas of expertise

Full-stack web development.

Main tech stack

- Java: 4+ years of professional experience
- Spring Boot: 4+ years of professional experience
- JPA: 4+ years of professional experience
- React: 2+ years of professional experience

- Node.js: 2+ years of professional experience

Jobs of interest

I'm interested in Java Backend developer jobs, Springboot to be precise, where I will be able to write Microservices and deploy them as Docker images, on either Azure or AWS.

Experience

SDET II 12/2021 - now

Tala 11 months

- Develop test automation suites to expand test coverage to all our microservices and integrate it into regression and release process
- Deliver framework for performance testing to be used on-demand and as part of regular testing
- Deliver tools to help test integration with 3rd party services (Payment Rails, SMS/Email, KYC (know your customer), Analytics, etc.)
- Integrate automated tests execution into the software development process
- Collaborate with squad leaders and other key stakeholders to strategize Product rollout
- Support and collaborate with cross-functional teams (Product, Data, Credit, and Business Development) in identifying automation areas to further increase the quality of our product
- Maintain, review, propose and implement improvements to existing frameworks, tools, and processes

Backend Developer / Microservices Engineer

07/2019 - 12/2021

Safaricom PLC

2 years and 5 months

- Servant leadership, developing talent across the business and outside the organization
- Agile mindset and behavior, championing and influencing a culture of growth mindset, self-leadership, and quality development
- Craft enablement through coaching, mentoring, facilitation, and teaching
- Strong relationship management skills as the chapter span various Squads and Tribes
- Business acumen and shaping a competitive customer-focused culture
- Technical acumen in capability delivery and thinking critically about the application of technologies to solve customer experience problems
- Effective problem solving and decision making to guide technology delivery in the Tribe squads
- Design, develop, and deploy, Java Spring boot-microservices on both clouds (AWS & Azure) and on-prem (Kubernetes & Openshift) clusters.

Software DevOps Engineer

07/2018 - 07/2019

Telkom Kenya

1 year

During this period, I am the lead DevOps engineer in Application Development and Systems support in various systems. I develop PLSQL Queries to create automated reports sent daily as Excel pivot tables. As the lead developer in developing integrations to Mpesa C2B API, enabling Telkom subscribers to be able to buy airtime from Telkom pay bill 777711 for prepaid customers and for postpaid Telkom subscribers to be able to pay their postpaid bill from their M-Pesa Wallet to Telkom pay bill 766600. Both applications are integrated into different internal systems, the billing system (OCS) for prepaid, the subscriber profile system (POS), third party airtime system(EJAZE), and finally postpaid billing and profile system(GPTO). All documentation of development, deployment, and support I uploaded in confluence, the company's collaborative wiki. All source code I uploaded to the repo.

Apart from the above integrations, I also perform daily operational support of internal systems, mainly the Telepin system, by checking transaction status performed by Trash subscribers and resolving daily LAN Support tickets, reported. I also designed and developed HA(High Availability) on application and DB servers, using open source tools i.e. corosync and pacemaker. As a developer, I am part of the development team, actively involved in the development and integration of T-Kash's new ESB i.e.(WSO2 API Gateway) that comprises, the development of APIs and Sequences in wso2 EI(Enterprise integrator), development of Java Microservices to integrate internal systems to the ESB and deployment into the APIGW environments using Jenkins jobs into Kube clusters(Kubernetes) that enable run the integrations within the ESB(WSO2 API Gateway).

Software Developer 08/2016 - 06/2018

Fintech Kenya Limited

1 year and 10 months

During this period, my major task has been to develop a USSD application and integrate it into the existing online system. The USSD application would facilitate the use of the existing service which is running on the android platform. The application is one that is going to be able to help users access their service cards which would allow them to do money transactions. Working on System integration of core banking system and Flex cube. Working with MySQL Server to perform Data mining, using SQL profiler to optimize Queries in the SQL DB. Writing Test scripts and Writing test evidence.

Customizing the finsacco product by adding a Death claim module which allows Sacco member's Next of kin and Beneficiary to claim funds of the deceased Sacco member and allow the Sacco to claim insurance from the insurer.

Working as the Lead developer for an online Bulk payment system for Citi Bank that facilitates Bulk KPLC (Electricity Bills) payments for their corporate clients from the convenience of their homes. The web application is hosted on IBM WebSphere, on a Linux server. It uses Java Spring MVC – Maven Jetty technologies.

Working with business users in gathering requirements and actively cataloging and supporting various issues and providing timely solutions. Using Pentaho Data Integration/Kettle to design all ETL processes to extract data from various sources including live system and external files, cleanse and then load the data into the target data warehouse. Writing UNIX shell scripts for file validations, payload ciphers, and scheduling batches and jobs for pre-processing and post-processing of the files. Converting existing SSIS Package to Pentaho 5.4 data Integration jobs. Designing Staging Databases and Data Warehouse DB using Star Schema.

Web and Mobile application Developer

03/2015 - 08/2016

Watu Technologies

1 year and 5 months

- Web Design and development.
- Mobile application development.
- Sourcing for new clientele and providing growth sales for Our products and services.

Creating Dashboards with Key Performance Indicators in SQL server 2014 Reporting Services.

Mobile Application Developer

10/2015 - 06/2016

mHealth Kenya

8 months

- Develop and design mobile systems. Integrate web services to the application and monitor the system traffic.
- Assist in web application development and systems enhancement.
- Build UI and learning modules for the users of the system.
- Enhance existing systems and add functionality.
- Brand development, web site traffic growth, web site UI and advertising(Social Media Strategy).

Education

Daystar University 01/2011 - 01/2015

BSc, Applied Computer Science

4 years

Languages

English Fluent